In 2012, when I painted the minaret of Jara Mosque
在2012年，当我图画Jara Mosque清真寺塔尖
in my hometown of Gabés, in the south of Tunisia,
在我的家乡突尼西亚南部城市加贝斯，
I never thought that graffiti would bring so much attention to a city.
我从没想过墙上的涂鸦会给这个城市带来如此多的关注。
At the beginning, I was just looking for a wall in my hometown,
一开始，我只是在我的家乡寻找一座墙面，
and it happened that the minaret was built in '94.
正好是94年建造的这个尖塔。
And for 18 years, those 57 meters of concrete stayed grey.
长达18年的时间里，57米高的混凝土依旧是灰色的。
When I met the imam for the first time, and I told him what I wanted to do,
当我第一次见到阿訇，我告诉他我的计划，
he was like, "Thank God you finally came,"
他说，“感谢主，你终于来了，”
and he told me that for years he was waiting for somebody
他告诉我，这么多年他都在等待某个人
to do something on it.
能够做些什么。
The most amazing thing about this imam is that he didn't ask me anything --
最神奇的是，这位阿訇没有问我任何有关
neither a sketch, or what I was going to write.
我要画些什么的问题。
In every work that I create, I write messages
在每个我创作的工作上，我书写信息
with my style of calligraffiti -- a mix of calligraphy and graffiti.
用我特有的calligraffiti——混杂着书法和涂鸦的方式。
I use quotes or poetry.
我书写引述或是诗文。
For the minaret, I thought that the most relevant message
就这个尖塔而言，我想最与它相关的是
to be put on a mosque should come from the Quran,
在清真寺上书写来自古兰经里的话，
so I picked this verse:
因此我选择了这条：
"Oh humankind, we have created you from a male and a female,
“人类啊，我把你们造成男性和女性，
and made you people and tribe, so you may know each other."
我把你们分成部落和民族，为的是你们互相了解。”
It was a universal call for peace, tolerance, and acceptance
这是普世的号召，为了和平，宽容和接纳
coming from the side that we don't usually portray in a good way in the media.
这样美好的讯息，我们并不时常从媒体上获得。
I was amazed to see how the local community reacted to the painting,
我很惊讶地看到当地居民是如何回应这样的图画的，
and how it made them proud to see the minaret getting so much attention
他们该多么骄傲，看到清真寺获得
from international press all around the world.
来自全球媒体的目光。
For the imam, it was not just the painting;
对那位阿訇来说，这并不只是图画；
it was really deeper than that.
比图画更加深邃。
He hoped that this minaret would become a monument for the city,
他希望这个尖塔能够成为这座城市的历史遗迹，
and attract people to this forgotten place of Tunisia.
吸引人们来到突尼西亚这个被遗忘的地方。
The universality of the message,
这条信息的广泛性，
the political context of Tunisia at this time,
此时突尼西亚的政治状况，
and the fact that I was writing Quran in a graffiti way
以及我用涂鸦方式书写古兰经这件事
were not insignificant.
并不是毫无建树的。
It reunited the community.
它使这个社群重新聚集起来。
Bringing people, future generations, together through Arabic calligraphy is what I do.
我所做的，就是用阿拉伯书画把人们，未来的每一代人连结起来。
Writing messages is the essence of my artwork.
我艺术作品的精髓是书写信息。
What is funny, actually, is that even Arabic-speaking people
好笑的是，事实上，以阿拉伯语为母语的人们
really need to focus a lot to decipher what I'm writing.
都需要花些时间来破译我写的文字内容。
You don't need to know the meaning to feel the piece.
感知这份艺术作品你并不需要知道它的意思。
I think that Arabic script touches your soul before it reaches your eyes.
我想，阿拉伯文字先触及了你的灵魂然后才是眼睛。
There is a beauty in it that you don't need to translate.
其中有一种无需翻译的美感。
Arabic script speaks to anyone, I believe;
阿拉伯文字和每个人相通，我相信：
to you, to you, to you, to anybody,
和你，和你，和你，和每一个人。
and then when you get the meaning,
然后，你知道了文字的含义，
you feel connected to it.
便产生共鸣。
I always make sure to write messages
我总是会确认书写那些
that are relevant to the place where I'm painting,
与我艺术创作地点相关联的文字。
but messages that have a universal dimension,
但是信息有全球化的不同维度，
so anybody around the world can connect to it.
使地球上的每个人都能与此连结。
I was born and raised in France, in Paris,
我在法国巴黎出生长大，
and I started learning how to write and read Arabic when I was 18.
18岁时我开始学习如何书写阅读阿拉伯文字。
Today I only write messages in Arabic.
今天我只用阿拉伯语书写信息。
One of the reasons this is so important to me,
对我而言最重要的原因之一，
is because of all the reaction that I've experienced all around the world.
是我在世界范围内的经验。
In Rio de Janeiro, I translated this Portuguese poem
在里约热内卢，我翻译了这首葡萄牙诗文
from Gabriela Tôrres Barbosa,
来自诗人Gabriela Torres Barbosa，
who was giving an homage to the poor people of the favela,
她向生活在贫民窟的穷人致敬，
and then I painted it on the rooftop.
我把这首诗写在了屋顶。
The local community were really intrigued by what I was doing,
当地的居民们 对我做的事感到好奇，
but as soon as I gave them the meaning of the calligraphy,
当我告诉他们这些图画文字的真正含义时，
they thanked me, as they felt connected to the piece.
他们感谢我，他们对艺术作品产生了共鸣。
In South Africa, in Cape Town,
在南非，开普敦，
the local community of Philippi
当地的菲律宾社群
offered me the only concrete wall of the slum.
把贫民窟仅有的一面水泥墙给我，
It was a school, and I wrote on it
它是一个学校，我在上面图画
a quote from Nelson Mandela,
我用了纳尔逊·曼德拉的名言，
saying, "[in Arabic],"
说道，“（阿拉伯语）”
which means, "It seems impossible until it's done."
“在事情未成功之前，一切总看似不可能。”
Then this guy came to me and said, "Man, why you don't write in English?"
有个人跟我说，“你为什么不用英文写呢？”
and I replied to him, "I would consider your concern legit if you asked me
我回答道，“我会认真考虑你的建议如果你问我
why I didn't write in Zulu."
为什么我不用祖鲁语写。”
In Paris, once, there was this event,
在巴黎，某次，有个活动，
and someone gave his wall to be painted.
某人让我在他的墙上图画。
And when he saw I was painting in Arabic,
当他看到我书写阿拉伯文的时候，
he got so mad -- actually, hysterical -- and he asked for the wall to be erased.
他很生气——事实上，歇斯底里——他要把那面墙上的字抹掉。
I was mad and disappointed.
我很生气，也很失望。
But a week later, the organizer of the event asked me to come back,
但是一周以后，那场活动的组织者请我回去，
and he told me that there was a wall right in front of this guy's house.
他告诉我那个人家门前有一面墙。
So, this guy --
所以，这个人......
(Laughter)
（笑声）
like, was forced to see it every day.
不得不每天看着我的图腾。
At the beginning, I was going to write, "[In Arabic],"
一开始，我打算用阿拉伯文书写，
which means, "In your face," but --
意思是，“你的脸上，”但是......
(Laughter)
（笑声）
I decided to be smarter and I wrote, "[In Arabic],"
我决定显得更聪明一些于是我写道，“（阿拉伯文）”
which means, "Open your heart."
意思是，“敞开心扉。”
I'm really proud of my culture,
我真心对我的文化感到自豪，
and I'm trying to be an ambassador of it through my artwork.
我希望用艺术作品传达它。
And I hope that I can break the stereotypes we all know,
我希望我能打破我们心中的刻板印象，
with the beauty of Arabic script.
用美丽的阿拉伯文字。
Today, I don't write the translation of the message anymore on the wall.
今天，我不再在墙上书写信息。
I don't want the poetry of the calligraphy to be broken,
我不希望打破图腾文字的诗文美感，
as it's art and you can appreciate it without knowing the meaning,
这门艺术你可以感受却不用知晓它的含义，
as you can enjoy any music from other countries.
正如同你能欣赏其他国家的音乐作品。
Some people see that as a rejection or a closed door,
有些人将它视为拒绝或是关闭的门，
but for me, it's more an invitation --
但对我来说，这更像是一个邀请--
to my language, to my culture, and to my art.
来欣赏我的语言我的文化，我的艺术作品。
Thank you.
谢谢。
(Applause)
（鼓掌）